Potter Club and Alumni Association; Records ua901.003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association Recordsca. 1920-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association
ua901.003
1.62 cubic ft.
The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association Records includes documents and objects related to the finances, activities, and history of the Club and subsequent Alumni Association. Materials related to the Edward E. Potter Club include financial settlements, photographs, correspondence, and meeting minutes. Materials related to the Alumni Association include Alumni addresses, memorabilia, and a newsletter. Objects in this collection include mugs, a blanket, stamp, letter opener, compact makeup, and ledger books.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Potter Club Records were originally donated to the University Libraries in 1989. Additional deposits were made by Don Kissel in 1992, and Paul Ward and Robert Umholtz in 1996
Biographical History
The Edward E. Potter Club, founded in 1931, began when thirteen undergraduates and alumni proposed to form a club in order to promote close friendships in a non-fraternal organization. They called it the "State Union." Prior to the formation of the Potter Club, the only men's social group was the Kappa Delta Rho fraternity. The president of the college, Abram R. Brubacher, approved of another men's social club, but he did not like the name "State Union." Therefore, Brubacher suggested that the Club adopt the name of Edward E. Potter in memory of a student killed in France during World War I. The Potter Club Alumni Association, Inc., was incorporated on February 17, 1948. Headquartered in Albany, the Alumni Association facilitated communication between past and present members of the Potter Club, provided educational and financial assistance to Potter Club members through awards and scholarships, and promoted the interests of the University and its alumni, in general.
Scope and Contents
The Potter Club Records consist of club papers, correspondence, and financial and membership information creating an incomplete record of the club's origin and activities from the 1930's through, approximately, 1970. Most of the documents come from and deal with the 1960's, including several versions of the club's constitution, evaluations, correspondence, minutes of the Board of Directors, alumni directories, and financial information. Much of the correspondence and minutes of club meetings address housing issues and behavioral standards for club members. The evaluations address the club's concerns over its adherence to the ideals represented by Edward E. Potter. Also included in the series are a petition, dated May 26, 1931, for recognition of the State Union which became the Potter Club, a list of twelve charter members of the club, and several editions of the Potter Post, the club's newspaper. The Potter Club Alumni Association, Inc., records contain correspondence, minutes, and financial information documenting the incorporation of the Association on February 17, 1948, and some of its activities until about 1970. The bulk of the collection was created in the 1960s. Included are the Certificate of Incorporation, Constitution of the Association, minutes of the Board of Directors, and several issues of the Potter Club Alumni Newsletter.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically.
Class reunions; State University of New York at Albany--History; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Periodicals; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Societies, etc.--Administration; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--United States--Societies, etc.--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Correspondence; Financial Records; Ephemera; Publications; UAlbany Student Groups; State University of New York at Albany
- Addresses - Members of Alumni Association, Undated (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 1)
- Constitution of Potter Club Alumni Association, Inc., Undated (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1948-1967 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Tax Status and Investments, 1950; 1962 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 4)
- Financial Statements, Final and Interim Reports, Proposed Budget, 1960-1965 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 5)
- Potter Club Housing Gift of Kisel '67, Undated (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 8)
- Ledger - Potter Club Alumni Association, 1949 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 10)
- Annual Meeting - Potter Club Alumni Association, 1967 June 10 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 11)
- Board of Directors-Potter Club Alumni Assoc: Minutes, Meetings, Correspondence, resolutions, trading accounts, 1964-1968; 1970 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 12)
- Potter Club Alumni Newsletter, 1963-1967 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 13)
- Prospects and Correspondence-Purchasing House for Potter Club, 1959-1961 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 14)
- Potter, Potter Club, and Potter Family Photograph, 1934; Undated (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 15)
- Potter Club Reunion - With Two Photographs, 2008; 2009 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 16)
- 75th Anniversary, 2006 (Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 17)
- Evaluation Committee, 1963 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 1)
- Financial Settlement, ca. 1967-1969 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 2)
- Financial Settlement, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 3)
- Supreme Court of The State of New York Appellate Division, 1963; Undated (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1950-1967 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 5)
- Quantity and Price Chart, Undated (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 6)
- House 1964-1965 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 7)
- New Contracts, Undated (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 8)
- Duties of Stewards, House Manager Waiters and Rules of House, Undated (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 9)
- Board Meeting Minutes, 1963 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 10)
- Materials-Board Meeting, 1962-1964 (Box 2 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R), Folder 11)
- Potter Club Blanket, Undated (Oversized 1, Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R))
- Potter Club Ledger Book, ca. 1920 (Oversized 2, Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R))
- Potter Club Ledger Book, 1948-1960 (Oversized 3, Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R))
- Potter Club Letter Opener, Stamp, Box, Compact Makeup, Bag, Undated (Oversized 4, Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R))
- Three Potter Mugs, Undated (Oversized 5, Box 1 (The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association R))